<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Code Podcast</title><link href="http://codepodcast.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://codepodcast.com/feeds/andrey-salomatin.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://codepodcast.com/</id><updated>2016-04-25T19:30:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Limits of technical podcasting</title><link href="http://codepodcast.com/podcast_blog0.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-04-25T19:30:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrey Salomatin</name></author><id>tag:codepodcast.com,2016-04-25:podcast_blog0.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="addthis_sharing_toolbox"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Podcasts about programming are all the same. Sure, hosts and topics are
different, but the format is the same. And this format – it has it's
limitations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a long time I thought this was the way to do podcasting – you gather with
your friends and discuss recent news, things you like and things you don't.
Sometimes you interview people to get an outside perspective. All of this is
recorded and then, after little polishing, you release it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it's an excellent way to introduce listeners to new techniques and to
developers in their community. This format has served well to shows like
&lt;a href="https://ruby5.codeschool.com/"&gt;Ruby5&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://devchat.tv/js-jabber/"&gt;JSJabber&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://mostlyerlang.com/"&gt;Mostly Erlang&lt;/a&gt; and many
others. I'm one of the hosts of a podcast like that. It's called
&lt;a href="https://radiojs.ru/"&gt;RadioJS&lt;/a&gt;, it's about JavaScript and it's in Russian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, there's a ton of subjects it's hard to talk about on these
podcasts: abstract concepts like design patterns, complicated systems like the
Internet and so on. Unless hosts know a lot about the topic and have spoken
publicly about it, it's hard to record a coherent story in one take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interviews on these shows are often shallow. "What are you working on?" "How
did you get into programming?" "What does your library/framework do?" Those
dialogs are not very technical. I feel like they often miss an opportunity to
dive deep into &lt;em&gt;person's work&lt;/em&gt;. Also, because it's usually one guest per
episode, there's no perspective. How are other people solving similar problem?
What do &lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; have to say about alternative solutions? These questions spin in
my head as I listen to an episode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;There's more to podcasting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We live in a golden age of podcasting. People make so many kinds of shows:
long form and short form, comedy and detective, narrative and conversational.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several months ago I've stumbled upon a show called &lt;a href="https://gimletmedia.com/show/startup/"&gt;StartUp&lt;/a&gt;. It's a
podcast about building a business. When I first heard it, I was amazed. The
quality of the show, the story, everything was done very professionally. I`ve
never heard anything like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later I've discovered &lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/podcasts/510298/ted-radio-hour"&gt;Ted Radio Hour&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="http://freakonomics.com/"&gt;Freekonomics&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/podcasts/510289/planet-money/"&gt;Planet Money&lt;/a&gt;. Their format was
different too. They would take one topic every episode and explore it in depth
from various perspectives. I knew it was time for a different kind of a
programming podcast, these shows gave me an idea about what to try first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Significant bits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together with my good friend &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/mikhail.be"&gt;Michael Beschastnov&lt;/a&gt; we've launched this
experiment. We'd choose one coding concept every episode, take several
interviews, heavily edit them, add music and try to make a story out of it. We
would talk usage, implementations and alternative solutions. We would give a
comprehensive overview of a technical concept in 30 minutes or less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We believe that ideas are more important than programming languages or
libraries or other tools. Once you understand the concept, it doesn't matter if
it's implemented in Python or in Node or in Haskell. You get how it works. With
this knowledge you can write new and debug existing code. Often you don't even
have to memorize the syntax of a target language to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is our goal – share concepts in programming that we find fascinating and
make an entertaining story out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Explore&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We love how this experiment is going so far. There're things we like about
&lt;strong&gt;Code&lt;/strong&gt; and things we don't, but the process of making it is super fun. Seeing
listeners feedback is very rewarding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this moment we have released 3 episodes. They make up one series
entitled &lt;em&gt;"Concurrency"&lt;/em&gt;. The show is taking shape, but we still have a backlog
of ideas to try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have dived into one format, but there are so many others. Programming
podcasts are all the same nowadays, but it doesn't have to be like that. I
would encourage &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; to experiment. Think of an idea for a show and then just
record it! Record one episode and share it with your friends and colleagues or
put it out on iTunes or SoundCloud. Send it to us, we are always searching for
new ways to do technical podcasting. If you don't have time to record it – send
the idea anyway!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a lot to explore in the world of programming podcasts, let's kick off
the scouting!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrey Salomatin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/filipovskii"&gt;@filipovskii&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="&amp;#109;&amp;#97;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;&amp;#58;&amp;#97;&amp;#110;&amp;#100;&amp;#114;&amp;#101;&amp;#121;&amp;#64;&amp;#99;&amp;#111;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#112;&amp;#111;&amp;#100;&amp;#99;&amp;#97;&amp;#115;&amp;#116;&amp;#46;&amp;#99;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;"&gt;&amp;#97;&amp;#110;&amp;#100;&amp;#114;&amp;#101;&amp;#121;&amp;#64;&amp;#99;&amp;#111;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#112;&amp;#111;&amp;#100;&amp;#99;&amp;#97;&amp;#115;&amp;#116;&amp;#46;&amp;#99;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Podcasts --&gt;

&lt;!-- People --&gt;
            &lt;img
            src="//www.google-analytics.com/__utm.gif?utmwv=4&amp;utmn=(8871190d-a853-45ca-9a4f-aceb14dbc7af)&amp;utmhn=codepodcast.com&amp;utmul=en-us&amp;utmcn=1&amp;utmr=0&amp;utm_medium=rss&amp;utmac=UA-73380046-1&amp;utmcc="&gt;</summary></entry></feed>